Other.001 19thCent
The College of Saint Rose Archives
19th Century Pamphlet and Broadside Collection
1837-1876
19thCent
The College of Saint Rose Archives
0.8 Linear feet (2 boxes)
Includes many pamphlets, broadsides, and publications from the 19th century, concerned mainly with abolition and temperance. The majority of items were written by Gerrit Smith.
Conditions Governing Access note
There are no restrictions to this collection.
Arrangement note
The collection is organized into three series by topic. The folders within each series are organized chronologically.
The series are:
Gerrit Smith, 1837-1873
Tracts For The Times, 1858-1860
Other Pamphlets, 1837-1876
Gerrit Smith (1797-1874)
A resident of Peterboro, NY, Gerrit Smith was a social activist and philanthropist very involved in many of the 19th century’s reform movements. Although he wrote for and donated to various causes, his particular interests lay in the anti-slavery, temperance, and woman's suffrage movements. He acted for these causes both in his letters and through politics. He organized the Liberty Party in 1840, which nominated him for the Presidential elections of 1848 and 1851. He did not accept either nomination; nor did he accept the nominations of the Industrial Congress (also in 1848) and the Land Reform Party (in 1856.) The Anti-Slavery Convention nominated him for governor of New York State in 1840 and 1858. He ran in the latter case and was defeated. Smith did eventually hold elected office as a member of the House of Representatives in 1853 and 1854. The Anti-Dramshop Party (later the National Prohibition party) was also partly his creation.
Smith’s religious convictions, from which stemmed his political convictions, were quite strong. He published a number of pamphlets on his spiritual beliefs, which he named the Religion of Reason. In 1843 he helped to found the Church of Peterboro, a non-denominational community, and funded the building of its chapel in 1847.
He is connected with many important and even well-known names. He was cousin to Elizabeth Cady Stanton, and father to Elizabeth Smith Miller (who invented the garment later known as bloomers.) His regular correspondents included Susan B. Anthony, Frederick Douglass, and John Brown. Although he shared the latter’s abolitionist viewpoints, their preferred methods differed greatly. Gerrit Smith helped to fund John Brown’s 1859 raid on Harper’s Ferry, Virginia; the depth of his knowledge regarding the plot is still in debate. Upon learning of its failure, the loss of life involved, and the possibility of his indictment as a co-conspirator, Smith had a breakdown and was briefly committed to an asylum in Utica.
Following this incident, Smith’s attitudes changed in small ways. Although always opposed to violence, and despite eventually supporting the North’s pursuit of the Civil War, he advocated a strict ethic of nonviolence. He continued some work in the abolition movements, although not with his former fervor. After the Civil War he pushed both reconciliation with the South and suffrage for black men – the latter at the expense of gaining the vote for women. To the end of his life he remained an active voice in other causes, and a generous philanthropist to the people he saw in need.
SEE ALSO: The following facilities contain substantial collections of material related to Gerrit Smith, from his pamphlets and collected writings to his original letters and other personal papers. The New York State Archives New York Public Library Syracuse University (much material available in digital format) Wichita State University Hamilton College (Alumni Collection)
TRACTS FOR THE TIMES
This Tracts for the Times series was published in Albany by the Ladies’ Religious Publications Society, part of the Division Street Unitarian Church. Many were written by Amory Dwight Mayo, contemporary pastor of the church.
SEE ALSO: Series 3, for the publication of a separate sermon by Rev. A.D. Mayo.
Amory Dwight Mayo (1823-1907): Mayo, a Unitarian preacher, was widely known for his published sermons. He worked in Massachusetts, Ohio, New York, and Pennsylvania. In Albany, he headed the Division Street Church from 1856-1863. In his later life he became more interested in education reform, and traveled the country (particularly the south) speaking on behalf of better school systems.
Samuel Longfellow (1819-1892): Samuel Longfellow was the brother of Henry Wadsworth Longfellow and a Unitarian preacher in the New England and Middle Atlantic states. He was renowned for his poetry, a talent he often turned to writing hymns.
Moncure Daniel Conway (1832-1907): Born in Virginia and a graduate of Harvard Divinity School, Conway preached in various churches during his life, through out the northern United States and in England. He began as a Methodist and like many of his contemporaries became a Unitarian through the Transcendentalist writings of Emerson. Although he later split with the Unitarians over their conservative practices, he remained a prolific writer and lecturer.
James Freeman Clarke (1810-1888): Clarke, a Unitarian preacher, worked most prominently in the southern states for the abolition of slavery. He also wrote several widely-read books on comparative theology, studying the similarities between Unitarians and more traditionalist Christian churches.
Samuel Osgood (1812-1880): A graduate of Harvard and Cambridge Divinity School, Osgood was initially most interested in spreading Unitarianism through the southern and western United States. He eventually preached in New England, and later New York City, and was “the acknowledged leader in the Unitarian Church” by the time he was 37. He was renowned for his speeches, both in his delivery and in the scholarship behind them.
Emerson W. Keyes: no information currently available
Cyrus Augustus Bartol (1813-1900): A graduate of Harvard Divinity School, Bartol was a transcendentalist who sought to free Unitarianism from unnecessary rituals. Although he was an admirer of Emerson, he was of a more conservative bent. He preached for the most part in New York City.
Orville Dewey (1794-1882): As a graduate of Andover Theological Seminary and Harvard Divinity, Dewey preached in both Massachusetts and New York. He was president of the American Unitarian Association from 1845 to 1847.
Samuel J. May (1797-1811): Samuel May was a leader in Unitarian efforts to end slavery, and often reviled by his own congregations for radical sermons and ideas. Among his concerns were the abolition of slavery, temperance, penal reform, better treatment for Native Americans, and pacifism. He eventually found a home at the Church of the Messiah in Syracuse, New York, where he preached for twenty years until his death. That community is now known as the May Memorial Unitarian Universalist Society.
OTHER PAMPHLETS
Reuben Dimond Mussey, M.D. (1780-1866): Dr. Reuben Mussey published a number of pamphlets on various health issues, particularly the ills of tobacco and alcohol use. He was a Professor of Surgery at Ohio Medical College and later the first president of the Academy of Medicine in Cincinnati.
L.S. Crandall (1844-19??): Lucien Stephen Crandall lived south of Syracuse variously in Cortland, where he was editor of the Courtland Democrat, and in Tully, where he was editor of the Southern Onondaga. He invented the Crandall Typewriter. Whether this is the same L.S. Crandall is uncertain.
Caleb Calkins (1814-????): Caleb Calkins was the personal secretary of Gerrit Smith. As a resident of Madison County he served as a trustee for the Peterboro Academy and later the Evans Academy. He was a justice of the peace for three terms, town supervisor of Smithfield in 1854, and served as representative to the State Assembly in 1866. As Caleb Calkins was a common name in the region, it is unclear whether the Caleb Calkins who signed this flyer is the same man or a relative.
- GERRIT SMITH, 1837-1873 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith to Edward C. Delavan, 11/6/1837 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith to President Schmucker, 06/19/1838 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith to Hon. F. Whittlesey of Rochester, 02/01/1845 (Box 1)
  - To those Ministers in the County of Madison, who refuse to preach politics, 07/15/1845 (Box 1)
  - The Poor Man’s Party. To the poor men of the County of Madison, 10/17/1846 (Box 1)
  - Abstract of the Argument, in the Public Discussion of the Question: “Are the Christians of a Given Community the Church of Such Community?”, 1847 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith to S.P. Chase, on the Unconstitutionality of Every Part of American Slavery, 1847 (Box 1)
  - Speech of Gerrit Smith, at the State Temperance Convention at Syracuse, January 19 and 20, 1848, on the Obligation of Civil Government to Prohibit the Traffic in Intoxicating Liquors. (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith to J.K. Ingalls, Editor of the Landmark, New-York, 08/15/1848 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith on Civil Government The True Office of Civil Government. A Speech in the City of Troy, 1851 (Box 1)
  - Speeches of Gerrit Smith in Congress, 1853-1854 - Speech of Gerrit Smith, in Congress, on the Reference of the President’s Message -Speech of Gerrit Smith on War - Homes for All. Speech of Gerrit Smith on the Homestead Bill - No Slavery in Nebraska: No Slavery in the Nation: Slavery an Outlaw. Speech of Gerrit Smith on the Nebraska Bill - Keep Government within its Limits. Speech of Gerrit Smith, on the Pacific Railroad, in the House of Representatives - Abolition of the Postal System. Speech of Gerrit Smith, in the House of Representatives - Speech of Gerrit Smith on Mexican Treaty and “Monroe Doctrine” - Letter of Gerrit Smith on the Reciprocity Treaty - Government Bound to Protect from the Dramshop. Speech of Gerrit Smith, on the Sale of Intoxicating Drinks in the City of Washington (Box 1)
  - Address of the “Anti-Dramshop Party” to the Independent Electors of Oswego County, 1854 (Box 1)
  - Homes For All. Speech of Gerrit Smith on the Homestead Bill. In Congress, 02/21/1854 (Box 1)
  - No Slavery in Nebraska: No Slavery in the Nation: Slavery an Outlaw. Speech of Gerrit Smith on the Nebraska Bill. In Congress, 4/6/1854 (Box 1)
  - Speech of Gerrit Smith, on Mexican Treaty and “Monroe Doctrine.” In Congress, 06/27/1854 (Box 1)
  - Controversy between New-York Tribune and Gerrit Smith, 1855 (Box 1)
  - The Arguments of Gerrit Smith and David J. Mitchell, and the Charge of Justice Mason, in a Trial for Murder, 1857 (Box 1)
  - Speech of Gerrit Smith, on Discriminating Tolls, Made in the Capitol at Albany, before the Canal and Rail Road Committees of the Senate, 03/25/1857 (Box 1)
  - Three Discourses on the Religion of Reason, by Gerrit Smith. - The Religion of Reason. A Discourse by Gerrit Smith in Peterboro, February 21, 1858 - The Religion of Reason. A Discourse by Gerrit Smith in Peterboro, January 23, 1859 - The Religion of Reason. A Discourse by Gerrit Smith in Peterboro, June 19th, 1859 - Letter to Mr. Goodell. August 13, 1859 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith and the Vigilant Association of the City of New-York, 1860 (Box 1)
  - Religion of Reason, No. 4. The One Test of Character. A Discourse by Gerrit Smith, 1860 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith on Religion - Letter to Doctor Cheever, March 6th, 1863 - Discourse in Peterboro. May 3, 1863. The Good See: The Bad Are Blind - Letter to Henry Ward Beecher. “Stonewall” Jackson. May 20th, 1863 - Funeral Discourse in Peterboro. June 28, 1863 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith on the Rebellion [Volume I] Speeches and Letters of Gerrit Smith (from January, 1863, to January, 1864) on the Rebellion - Letter to Governor [Horatio] Seymour. January 12th, 1863 - Stand by the Government. Speech in Albany, February 27, 1863 - Denying Suffrage Even to Soldiers! - Speech at Loyal League Convention in Utica, May 26th, 1863 - Speech on the Rebellion and the Draft in Oswego, July 29th, 1863 - Speech at Young Men’s Mass Convention, in Syracuse, September 3d, 1863 - The Rebellion. Speech in Montreal, December 19th, 1863 - On the Country. Letter to Hon. D. C. Littlejohn. January 14th, 1864 - Letter to Hon. Preston King. January 29, 1864 (Box 1)
  - Be Natural! A Discourse by Gerrit Smith in Peterboro, 11/20/1864 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith on the Rebellion. Volume II Speeches and Letters of Gerrit Smith (from January, 1864, to January, 1865) on the Rebellion - On the Constitution. February 24, 1864 - On the Fort Pillow and Plymouth Massacres. April 26, 1864 - Letter to Mrs. Stanton on the Presidential Question [Elizabeth Cady Stanton, his cousin] June 6, 1864 - Letter to Messrs. Wade and Davis. August 8, 1864 - On McClellan’s Nomination and Acceptance. September 14, 1864 - Letter to Mr. Kirkland. September 24, 1864 - To the Rank and File of the Democratic Party. October 20, 1864 - Extract from a Discourse in Peterboro, November 20, 1864 - Letter to Senator Sumner. December 5, 1864 - The Constitution, Reconstruction, and the Proclamation. Speech at Cooper Institute, New-York. January 4, 1865 (Box 1)
  - No Treason in Civil War Speech of Gerrit Smith, at Cooper Institute, New-York, 06/08/1865 (Box 1)
  - Temperance. In Which Was the Convention Right?, 8/18/1865 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith to J.B. Edwards. Rail Roads, 10/10/1867 (Box 1)
  - Chicago National Temperance Convention. An Explanation. Address of the National Temperance Convention held in Chicago, September 1 and 2, 1869 (Box 1)
  - Lake Ontario Shore Railroad. Letter From Gerrit Smith, 04/16/1870 (Box 1)
  - Address of the Convention of the New York Anti-Dramshop Party, Held in the City of Syracuse, August 17th 1870, to the People of the State of New York. Reported by Gerrit Smith, 8/17/1870 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith to His Colored Brethren, 10/26/1870 (Box 1)
  - The Peterboro Anti-Dramshop Voters to the Madison County Anti-Dramshop Voters, 1/20/1871 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith on Temperance. To the Thoughtful and Candid of the County of Madison, 3/8/1871 (Box 1)
  - The West Point Mob, 3/13/1871 (Box 1)
  - Speech of Gerrit Smith (to His Neighbors) in Peterboro, N.Y., 6/22/1872 (Box 1)
  - Criticism of N.Y. Tribune on Gerrit Smith, 8/9/1872 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith to Horace Greeley, 10/1/1872 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith to the Anti-Dramshop Party. A Mutual Disappointment!, 11/6/1872 (Box 1)
  - Gerrit Smith to Susan B. Anthony, 2/5/1873 (Box 1)
  - A Letter From the Hon. Gerrit Smith, to the Cuban Anti-Slavery Committee, New York, 2/14/1873 (Box 1)
  - Let Crushed Cuba Arise! Substance of the Speech of Gerrit Smith, in Syracuse, 7/4/1873 (Box 1)
  - Woman Suffrage Above Human Law. Letter From Gerrit Smith [to Susan B. Anthony], 8/15/1873 (Box 1)
  - Spain.--- Cuba, 12/1/1873 (Box 1)
- TRACTS FOR THE TIMES, 1858-1860 (Box 2)
  - Mayo, Rev. A.D. (Amory Dwight) – Liberal Christianity. Tracts for the Times: No. 1, 1858 (Box 2)
  - Mayo, Rev. A.D. (Amory Dwight) – Liberal Christianity: A Practical Religion. Tracts for the Times: No. 3, 1859 (Box 2)
  - Longfellow, Rev. Samuel – The Father: The Only and the Sufficient God. Tracts for the Times: No. 4, 1859 (Box 2)
  - Conway, Rev. M.C. (Moncure Daniel) – The Natural History of the Devil. Tracts for the Times: No. 5, 1859 (Box 2)
  - Mayo, Rev. A.D. (Amory Dwight) – What is Infidelity. Tracts for the Times: No. 6, 1859 (Box 2)
  - Clarke, James Freeman – A Church and its Methods. Tracts for the Times: No. 9, 1859 (Box 2)
  - Osgood, Rev. Samuel, D.D. – The Bottomless Pit: Thoughts Upon the Reality of Hell. Tracts for the Times: No. 10, 1859 (Box 2)
  - Mayo, Rev. A.D. (Amory Dwight) – The Great Reformation of the Nineteenth Century. Tracts for the Times: No. 11, 1859 (Box 2)
  - Keyes, Emerson W. – A Case of Evangelical Church Discipline. Tracts for the Times: No. 12, 1859 (Box 2)
  - Bartol, Rev. C.A. (Cyrus Augustus) – Cornering Religion. Tracts for the Times: Vol. 2, Whole No. 13, No. 1, 1860 (Box 2)
  - Dewey, Rev. Orville – On the Alleged Decay of Faith. Tracts for the Times: Vol. 2, Whole No. 11, No. 2, 1860 (Box 2)
  - Mayo, Rev. A.D. (Amory Dwight) – A Religious Experience. Tracts for the Times: Vol. 2, Whole No. 15, No. 3, 1860 (Box 2)
  - May, Rev. Samuel J. – What do Unitarians Believe? Tracts for the Times: Vol. 2, Whole No. 16, No. 4, 1860 (Box 2)
- OTHER PAMPHLETS, 1837-1876 (Box 2)
  - Mussey, Reuben D., M.D. – Prize Essay of Ardent Spirits, and its Substitutes as a Means of Invigorating Health, 1837 (Box 2)
  - The South Bend Fugitive Slave Case, Involving the Right to a Writ of Habeas Corpus, 1851 (Box 2)
  - Mayo, Rev. A.D. (Amory Dwight) – Herod, John and Jesus; or American Slavery and its Christian Cure. A Sermon Preached in Division Street Church, Albany N.Y., 1860 (Box 2)
  - Crandall, L.S. – The Anti-Dramshop Idea. Issue from the office of “The Anti-Dram Shop,” No. 4 Convention Hall Block, Syracuse, N.Y. For gratuitous distribution. Address by L.S. Crandall, delivered in City Hall, Syracuse, 6/16/1872 (Box 2)
  - Calkins, Caleb – Important To Those Seeking Safe and Profitable Investments, and Those Seeking Homes, 9/26/1876 (Box 2)